<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>IKVM.NET Installation</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
  <section>
    <title>Installation</title>
      <p>The installation procedure for both Windows and Linux is straightforward.
      After <link href="site:download">downloading</link> the binary distribution, simply extract the 
      files from the archive. Open a command or shell window, cd to ikvm\bin, and type</p>
      <p xml:space="preserve"><code>       ikvm</code></p>
      <p>If your system is operating correctly, you should see the following output:</p>
      <p xml:space="preserve"><code>
    usage: ikvm [-options] &lt;class> [args...]
            (to execute a class)
      or ikvm -jar [-options] &lt;jarfile> [args...]
            (to execute a jar file)
          </code>...</p>
      <p>For convenience, you may wish to add the \ikvm\bin folder to your system's path, but this is not required.  
      Now, if all you want to do is use IKVM as a Java VM, you're done -- no further configuration is needed.
      If you want to use IKVM for .NET / Mono development, read the configuration instructions below.
      </p>
    </section>
    
      <section>
        <title>Configuration for Development</title>
        <p>If you plan to do .NET development with IKVM.NET, you may wish to do the following:</p>
        <ul><li>Download the <fork href="ext:jikes">Jikes compiler</fork>
        <p>If you plan to develop code in Java that runs in .NET, you will need a Java compiler. IKVM.NET does not
              come with a compiler. You may use any Java compiler that emits standard Java .class files. Jikes is an excellent
              open source, fast Java compiler that is available for many platforms.</p></li>
        <li>Windows: Install IKVM dll's in the Global Assembly Cache
        <p>When running .NET applications in Windows that use IKVM dll's, the .NET framework must be able to locate the dll's. 
        It looks in the Global Assembly Cache, then in the current directory. If you want to be able to do development
        without having the dll's in the current directory, you must install them in the Global Assembly Cache.
        To do this in Windows,  access the Microsoft .NET Framework
        Configuration item in the Windows Control Panel, and add the assemblies to the Assembly Cache.
        At minimum, you will want to install the IKVM.GNU.Classpath.dll and IKVM.Runtime.dll.
        </p>
        </li>
        </ul>
        <p></p>
      </section>

</body>
</document>
